(upbeat music)
(欢快的音乐)
Welcome, in the last lecture,
欢迎大家，在上一次的讲座中、
we successfully set up this physics climb function.
我们成功地设置了这个物理学爬升功能。
One important thing here to mention is,
这里要提到的一件重要事情是、
this function here, same as take,
这个函数在这里，和拿的一样、
will be run every frame.
将在每一帧运行。
So once we are inside of the climb state,
所以一旦我们进入了爬升状态、
this physics climb here will be constantly run.
这个物理爬升函数就会持续运行。
We can use this function input delta time
我们可以利用这个函数输入的delta时间
to help us to achieve many different things we need.
来帮助我们实现许多我们需要的不同事情。
So in this lecture, we'll look at how we can process
在这个讲座中，我们将看看我们如何能够处理
all the climbable surfaces info.
所有的可爬升表面信息。
And let's try to narrow it down in here.
而在这里，让我们试着缩小它的范围。
What exactly do we need to process?
我们到底需要处理什么？
Well, there are two pieces of information that we need.
嗯，我们需要两部分信息。
So first, we'll need the current climbable surface location.
首先，我们需要当前的可爬升表面的位置。
And the second one,
第二件事、
we'll need the current climbable surface normal.
我们需要当前可爬升表面的法线。
These two vectors here are essential for us
这两个向量对于我们
to do the calculation we need.
来进行我们需要的计算。
So we'll first look at this climbable surface location.
所以我们先看一下这个可爬升面的位置。
And for the math that we need to do later,
而对于我们后面需要做的数学运算、
is mainly about vector subtraction.
主要是关于向量的减法。
And just to provide you with a simple example,
只是为了给你提供一个简单的例子、
so you can see in here, I have two 2D points.
所以你可以看到这里，我有两个2D点。
And the first one, let's say it has a value of five in the X
第一个点，假设它在X轴上的数值是5，在Y轴上的数值是3。
and a value of three in the Y, I'm gonna call it V1.
和一个Y值为3的点，我把它叫做V1。
And the second one, let's say it has a value of three
第二个点，假设它的数值为3
in the X and one for the Y, I'm gonna call it V2.
X值为3，Y值为1，我就叫它V2。
So here we are using two simple vectors
所以在这里我们用两个简单的向量
to represent their locations.
来表示它们的位置。
And now if I use V1 to subtract V2,
现在如果我用V1减去V2、
what's the result that I'm gonna get?
我将得到什么结果？
So let's using five to subtract three
所以我们用5减去3
and using three to subtract one.
和用三减一。
And the result will be two for the X and two for the Y.
结果将是X为2，Y为2。
And this is the new vector that we're gonna get.
这就是我们要得到的新向量。
And if I move this vector to here
如果我把这个向量移到这里
and use these three vectors to form a triangle,
并用这三个向量组成一个三角形、
this is my final result.
这就是我的最终结果。
And that's the math we need.
这就是我们需要的数学知识。
So by using one vector to subtract the other,
所以通过用一个向量减去另一个向量，
we can get a vector pointing from the second one
我们可以得到一个矢量，从第二个矢量指向第一个矢量
to the first one.
到第一个。
So now this position here, this is our character
所以现在这个位置，是我们的角色
and this position here,
和这个位置、
this is our climbable surface location.
这是我们的可攀爬表面的位置。
But doing a simple subtraction here,
但在这里做一个简单的减法、
we can get a vector pointing from character
我们可以得到一个矢量，指向从角色
to the climbable surface.
到可爬升表面。
And we can perform all sorts of calculation we need in here.
我们可以在这里进行各种我们需要的计算。
And just to examine what we've just learned,
为了检验我们刚刚学到的东西、
I have a challenge for you.
我有一个挑战给你。
So here I have the same vectors
这里我有同样的向量
and this time I'm gonna use V2 to subtract V1,
这次我要用V2来减去V1、
what is the new vector that I'm gonna get.
我将得到的新向量是什么。
Pause the video now and see if you can solve this by yourself.
现在暂停视频，看看你是否能自己解决这个问题。
Welcome back.
欢迎回来。
So by using the V2 to subtract V1,
所以通过使用V2减去V1、
we'll be using three to subtract five,
我们将用3减去5、
we'll get negative two.
我们会得到负2。
And use one to subtract three,
再用1减去3、
we'll get another negative two.
我们会得到另一个负2。
So this is our result and this is our new vector.
所以这是我们的结果，这是我们的新矢量。
And if I move this vector to this spot
如果我把这个向量移到这个地方
and use these three vectors to form another triangle,
并用这三个向量组成另一个三角形、
this is the result that I'm gonna get.
这就是我将得到的结果。
You can see comparing to the last vector,
你可以看到，与上一个向量相比，这两个点之间的距离仍然很小、
the distance between these two points are still the same,
这两点之间的距离仍然是一样的、
but the vector here is the exact opposite.
但这里的矢量却完全相反。
So we are getting a vector pointing from V1 to V2.
所以我们得到了一个从V1指向V2的向量。
And that's another important math calculation
这是另一个重要的数学计算
that we'll do later.
我们稍后会做。
So if we want to inverse the direction of a vector,
所以，如果我们想反转一个矢量的方向、
we can simply multiply it with an active one,
我们可以简单地将其与一个活动的方向相乘、
keep that in mind.
牢记这一点。
All right, now that you know what we need to do
好了，现在你知道我们需要做什么了
with this clampable surface location,
要做的事情、
let's look at what we can do
让我们来看看我们能用这个可夹持表面的法线做什么
with this clampable surface normal.
我们来看看我们可以用这个可夹持表面的法线做什么。
And first we'll need to understand
首先，我们需要了解
what is a surface normal.
什么是曲面法线。
So when dealing with surface normals,
所以在处理表面法线的时候
we're mostly gonna be dealing with face normal
我们主要是要处理面法线
and vertex normal.
和顶点法线。
So normals, they are univectors,
所以法线，它们是单向量、
they only have a length of one.
它们的长度只有一个。
The valuable information you can provide
你可以提供的有价值的信息
is the direction information.
是方向信息。
You can see for the face normal here,
你可以在这里看到面部法线、
it's simply just a line pointing straight out from the face.
它只是一条从脸部直接指向外面的线。
And it can tell us which direction this face is facing.
它可以告诉我们这个脸是朝哪个方向的。
And same thing goes for the vertex normal in here.
这里的顶点法线也是如此。
It can tell us which direction this vertices is facing.
它可以告诉我们这个顶点朝向哪个方向。
And that's exactly what we need to do our calculation.
而这正是我们需要做的计算。
All right, that's the theory part, that's star coding.
好了，这就是理论部分，这就是星形编码。
Go back to my Visual Studio,
回到我的Visual Studio、
I'm gonna go to the header file.
我将转到头文件。
And inside of this ClampCore variables,
在这个ClampCore变量里面、
I'm gonna create two new variables.
我将创建两个新的变量。
So the first one is gonna be an S vector.
因此，第一个将是一个S向量。
I'm gonna call it currentClimbableSurfaceLocation.
我将把它称为currentClimbableSurfaceLocation。
And the second vector,
而第二个矢量、
I'm gonna call it currentClimbableSurfaceNormal.
我将把它称为currentClimbableSurfaceNormal。
And if you recall, we are using a capsule trace
如果你还记得，我们正在使用一个胶囊轨迹
to capture all of those different surfaces in front of us.
来捕捉我们面前的所有这些不同的表面。
So very likely that we'll have multiple hit locations
因此，我们很可能会有多个撞击位置
and multiple surface normals.
和多个表面法线。
And we'll need to find a way to combine them as a whole.
而我们需要找到一种方法将它们作为一个整体来组合。
So I'm gonna expand this ClampCore.
所以我将扩展这个ClampCore。
And under this physics clamp,
在这个物理钳子下面
I'm gonna create another function.
我将创建另一个函数。
So I'm gonna call this function
所以我将调用这个函数
processClimbableSurfaceInfo.
processClimbableSurfaceInfo。
And I'm gonna create a function definition.
然后我要创建一个函数定义。
I'm gonna place this function under this physics clamp.
我将把这个函数放在这个物理夹子下面。
So place it in here.
所以把它放在这里。
And first thing I'm gonna call this function.
我首先要调用这个函数。
So scroll up and set a physics clamp.
所以向上滚动并设置一个物理钳。
So first I'm gonna call the function
所以我首先要调用这个函数
choiceClimbableSurfaces.
choiceClimbableSurfaces。
Since this physics clamp will be run every frame,
因为这个物理钳制将在每一帧运行、
once we are inside of the clamp state,
一旦我们进入了钳制状态、
we'll be using this function here
我们将在这里使用这个函数
to constantly fill in the useful information we need.
来不断填入我们需要的有用信息。
And in case you forget, inside of this function,
为了防止你忘记，在这个函数里面、
we're doing the capsule trace
我们正在做胶囊追踪
and we are assigning the hit results to this array.
并将命中结果分配给这个数组。
All right, I'm gonna scroll up.
好了，我要向上滚动。
And below this function,
在这个函数下面、
I'm gonna call the function that we just created.
我将会调用我们刚刚创建的那个函数。
So it'll be this processClimbableSurfaceInfo.
所以它将是这个processClimbableSurfaceInfo。
So place it in here.
所以把它放在这里。
All right, let's look at how we shall implement this function.
好的，让我们看看我们应该如何实现这个函数。
So the first thing that I want to do,
所以我想做的第一件事是、
I'm gonna use the member variable
我将使用成员变量
currentClimbableSurfaceLocation.
currentClimbableSurfaceLocation。
And I'm gonna set it to a zero vector.
我将把它设置为一个零矢量。
And I'm gonna be doing the same thing
我将对currentClimbableSurfaceNormal做同样的事情。
to the currentClimbableSurfaceNormal.
对currentClimbableSurfaceNormal做同样的事情。
And copy this, paste it in here.
然后复制这个，把它粘贴到这里。
And the next thing that I'm gonna check.
接下来我要检查的是。
So if this ClimbableSurface is trace the results.
所以如果这个ClimbableSurface是追踪结果。
So if this array is empty,
所以如果这个数组是空的、
then I'm gonna return out of this function.
那么我就会从这个函数中返回。
Since this function here will also be run every frame,
因为这个函数也会在每一帧运行、
it's important that we zero out
重要的是，我们要在开始时把
these two member variables at the beginning.
这两个成员变量在开始时归零是很重要的。
All right, once we get past this if check,
好了，一旦我们通过了这个if检查，我将在这个数组中进行循环、
I'm gonna loop through this array.
我将在这个数组中进行循环。
So it's gonna be a range-based for loop.
所以这将是一个基于范围的for循环。
It's gonna be const hit result reference.
这将是一个const hit result reference。
I'm gonna call this trace hit result.
我将把这个称为追踪命中结果。
And I'm gonna loop through this array.
然后我将在这个数组中循环。
And as for handling multiple surface normals
至于如何处理多个表面法线
and multiple impact points,
和多个撞击点、
this is what I like to do.
这是我喜欢做的。
So first I'm gonna add
所以我首先要把
all of these different locations together.
所有这些不同的位置加在一起。
So it's gonna be plus equal,
所以要加的是相等的、
the trace the result,
追踪结果、
the impact point.
影响点。
And I'm gonna add all of these normals together.
然后我要把所有这些法线加在一起。
So it's gonna be plus equal,
所以它将会是加等号的、
trace the hit result,
追踪撞击的结果、
the impact normal.
撞击的法线。
And once we've extract all of this information,
一旦我们提取了所有这些信息、
at the end of this function,
在这个函数的结尾，
I'm gonna divide this current ClimbableSurface location
我将把这个当前的可攀爬表面的位置
by the number of elements inside of this array.
除以这个数组中的元素数量。
So I'm gonna use the function num in here.
所以我将在这里使用函数num。
So by doing this,
因此，通过这样做、
we'll be getting an average location
我们将得到一个平均位置
from all of these possible locations
从所有这些可能的位置
inside of this array.
在这个数组里面。
And for the normal here,
而对于这里的法线，我们可以简单地将其标准化、
we can simply normalize it.
我们可以简单地将其归一化。
So I'm gonna copy this variable name.
所以我将复制这个变量名。
So this one is gonna equal to get safe normal.
因此，这个变量将等于得到安全法线。
And that's pretty much it.
这就差不多了。
And one last thing that I want to do,
最后一件事是我想做的、
so I'm gonna scroll down
所以我将向下滚动
to this trace ClimbableSurface is,
到这个追踪ClimbableSurface、
I'm gonna delete this true.
我要删除这个真。
So I only want to draw the debug shape for one frame
所以我只想在一帧内画出调试形状
since we're calling this function every frame
因为我们每一帧都要调用这个函数
once we start climbing.
一旦我们开始攀登。
And I'm gonna delete these two truths.
而我要删除这两个真相。
So I don't need to see the debug lines
所以我不需要看到调试线
for this trace from iHeight.
追踪iHeight的情况。
And I'm gonna press Control+B to compile.
然后我要按Control+B来编译。
All right, I have a successful compile.
好的，我有一个成功的编译。
And to prove this is working,
为了证明这是在工作、
I'm gonna print these two values out.
我要把这两个值打印出来。
So I'm gonna use debugged print.
所以我将使用debugged print。
And the message here,
还有这里的信息、
so this will be the ClimbableSurface location.
所以这将是ClimbableSurface的位置。
And I'm gonna append another string in here.
我还要在这里添加一个字符串。
So convert this to a string.
所以把它转换成一个字符串。
And for the color, I'm gonna fill in Fcolor,
对于颜色，我要填入Fcolor、
sine.
正弦。
And for this in key, I'm gonna give it a value of one.
对于这个键，我要给它一个1的值。
Then I'm gonna copy this function.
然后我要复制这个函数。
And I'm gonna paste it in here.
然后把它粘贴到这里。
So this one, this is the surface normal.
所以这一个，是表面法线。
And I'm gonna copy this normal
我将复制这个法线
and paste it in here.
并把它粘贴到这里。
And this time I'm gonna change its color from sine to red
这次我将把它的颜色从正弦改为红色
and change its in key to two.
并把它的输入键改为2。
All right, I'm gonna press Control+F5
好的，我将按Control+F5
to launch my editor back.
来启动我的编辑器。
Go back to my editor, I'm gonna press play in here.
回到我的编辑器，我将在这里按播放键。
Then I'm gonna go to a ClimbableSurface and press F.
然后我要去找一个可攀登的表面，按F键。
And you can see there's my surface location
你可以看到这里有我的表面位置
and surface normal.
和表面法线。
And we're doing this capsule trace every frame.
我们在每一帧都做这个胶囊追踪。
That's great.
这很好。
And I'm sure you can notice that we can move our character
我相信你可以注意到，我们可以再次移动我们的角色了。
again, but in a very weird way.
但是以一种非常奇怪的方式。
And that's because we have our physics function ready.
这是因为我们已经准备好了我们的物理学功能。
We should have our movement back
我们应该恢复我们的运动
and we'll still need to handle to snap our movement
而我们仍然需要处理将我们的运动与
to the ClimbableSurface.
到可攀爬表面上。
And we'll do that later.
我们稍后会做这个。
But for now, our processing is working as expected.
但是现在，我们的处理方法正在按预期进行。
So this is the function for processing that I just created
所以这是我刚刚创建的处理函数
and it's all the processing we need.
这就是我们需要的所有处理。
Now with these two variables ready,
现在有了这两个变量的准备、
starting from next lecture,
从下一讲开始、
we can finally start doing some vector math.
我们终于可以开始做一些矢量数学了。
Feel free to refer back to the video if you need help.
如果你需要帮助，可以随时回看视频。
And I'll see you in the next lecture.
我们在下一节课再见。
(upbeat music)
(欢快的音乐)